Okay, I have no idea what we're going to play.
حسنا، ليست لدي أدنى فكرة عما سنعزفه.
I won't be able to tell you what it is until it happens.
لن أكون قادرا على إخباركم ما هو حتى يحدث.
I didn't realize there was going to be a little music before.
لم أدرك أنه سيكون هناك القليل من الموسيقى قبل.
So I think I'm going to start with what I just heard.
وبالتالي أعتقد أنني سأبدأ بما سمعته للتو.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Okay, so first of all,
حسنا، أولا وقبل كل شيء.
let's welcome Mr. Jamire Williams on the drums,
دعونا نرحب بالسيد جامير وليامز على الطبل،
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Burniss Travis on the bass,
بورنيس ترافيس على الجهير،
and Mr. Christian Sands on the piano.
والسيد كريستيان ساندز على البيانو.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So the bandstand, as we call it,
وبالتالي فمنصة الفرقة، كما نسميها،
this is an incredible space.
هي فضاء مذهل.
It is really a sacred space.
إنه حقا مكان مقدس.
And one of the things that is really sacred about it
وأحد الأشياء المقدسة حقا بخصوصه
is that you have no opportunity to think about the future,
هو أنه ليس لديك أي فرصة للتفكير في المستقبل،
or the past.
أو الماضي.
You really are alive right here in this moment.
أنت حقا حي في هذه اللحظة بالضبط هنا .
There are so many decisions being made
هناك الكثير من القرارات التي يتم اتخاذها
when you walk on the bandstand.
حين تمشي على منصة الفرقة.
We had no idea what key we were going to play in.
لم تكن لدينا أدنى فكرة عن المفتاح الذي سنعزف عليه.
In the middle, we sort of made our way
في الوسط، كنا نوعا ما نرسم الطريق
into a song called "Titi Boom."
نحو أغنية تدعى "تيتي بوم."
But that could have happened -- maybe, maybe not.
لكن ذلك يمكن أن يحصل -- ربما، أو ربما لا.
Everyone's listening. We're responding.
الجميع يستمع. نحن نتجاوب.
You have no time for projected ideas.
ليس لديك وقت للأفكار المتوقعة.
So the idea of a mistake:
وبالتالي فكرة الخطأ:
From the perspective of a jazz musician,
من وجهة نظر موسيقي جاز،
it's easier to talk about someone else's mistake.
من الأسهل أن تتحدث عن خطأ شخص آخر.
So the way I perceive a mistake when I'm on the bandstand --
وبالتالي الطريقة التي أتصور بها الخطأ حين أكون على منصة الفرقة --
first of all, we don't really see it as a mistake.
أولا وقبل كل شيء، لا نراها في الواقع على أنها خطأ.
The only mistake lies
الخطأ الوحيد يكمن
in that I'm not able to perceive
في كوني غير قادر على تصور
what it is that someone else did.
ما الذي قام به ذلك الآخر.
Every "mistake" is an opportunity in jazz.
كل "خطأ" هو فرصة في الجاز.
So it's hard to even describe
لذلك فمن الصعب حتى وصف
what a funny note would be.
ما قد تكونه نوتة مضحكة.
So for example, if I played a color, like we were playing on a palette,
إذن على سبيل المثال، إن عزفت لونا، كما كنا نفعل على اللوحة،
that sounded like this ...
بدا مثل هذا ..
(Music)
(ضحك)
So if Christian played a note -- like play an F.
وهكذا إن عزف كريستيان نوتة -- مثل F.
See, these are all right inside of the color palette.
ترون أن هذه كلها موجودة داخل لوحة الألوان.
If you played an E.
إن عزفتم E.
See, these all lie right inside
ترون كل هذا الضوء يوجد تماما داخل
of this general emotional palette that we were painting.
هذه اللوحة العاطفية التي كنا نرسم.
If you played an F# though,
لكن إن عزفتم F#،
(Dissonance)
(تناشز)
to most people's ears, they would perceive that as a mistake.
بالنسبة لآذان معظم الناس، سيتصورون ذلك على أنه خطأ.
So I'm going to show you, we're going to play just for a second.
وبالتالي سأريكم، سنعزف للحظة.
And we're going to play on this palette.
وسنعزف على هذه اللوحة.
And at some point, Christian will introduce this note.
وفي لحظة معينة، كريستيان سيدخله هذه النوتة.
And we won't react to it.
ولن نتفاعل معها.
He'll introduce it for a second
سيدخلها للحظة
and then I'll stop, I'll talk for a second.
ثم يتوقف، سأتحدث للحظة.
We'll see what happens when we play with this palette.
سنرى، ماذا سيحدث حين نلعب بهذه اللوحة.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
So someone could conceptually perceive that as a mistake.
وبالتالي قد يتصور أحدهم ذلك على أنه خطأ.
The only way that I would say it was a mistake
الخطأ الوحيد الذي قد أتحدث عنه
is in that we didn't react to it.
هو أننا لم نتفاعل معه.
It was an opportunity that was missed.
كان هناك فرصة ضيعناها.
So it's unpredictable. We'll paint this palette again.
وبالتالي فهو غير متوقع. سنلون هذه اللوحة مجددا.
He'll play it. I don't know how we'll react to it, but something will change.
سيعزفها. لا أعرف كيف سنتجاوب معها، لكن شيئا ما سيتغير.
We'll all accept his ideas,
سنتقبل جميعا أفكاره.
or not.
أو لا.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
So you see, he played this note.
إذن ترون، قد عزف نوتته.
I ended up creating a melody out of it.
وانتهيت بإنشاء لحن اعتمادا عليها.
The texture changed in the drums this time.
تغير النسيج في الطبل هذه المرة.
It got a little bit more rhythmic, a little bit more intense
صار أكثر إيقاعية بقليل، أكثر حدة بقليل
in response to how I responded to it.
كاستجابة للكيفية التي تجاوبت بها معه.
So there is no mistake.
وبالتالي ليست هناك أي أخطاء.
The only mistake is if I'm not aware,
الخطأ الواحد هو إن لم أكن واعيا،
if each individual musician is not aware
إن كان كل موسيقي بذاته غير واع
and accepting enough of his fellow band member
ويتقبل ما هو كاف من زملائه في الفرقة
to incorporate the idea and we don't allow for creativity.
لدمج الفكرة وعدم السماح بالإبداع.
So jazz, this bandstand is absolutely amazing.
وهكذا فالجاز، منصة الفرقة هذه هي بالفعل بديعة.
It's a very purifying experience.
إنها تجربة تطهير.
And I know that I speak for all of us when I tell you that we don't take it for granted.
وأعرف أنني أتحدث باسمنا جميعا هنا حين أقول أننا لا نعتبر ذلك مسلما به.
We know that to be able to come on the bandstand and play music is a blessing.
نعرف أن مجيئك إلى منصة الفرقة وعزفك الموسيقى، هو نعمة.
So how does this all relate to behavioral finance?
وبالتالي ما علاقة كل هذا بالسلوك المالي؟
Well we're jazz musicians,
حسنا نحن موسيقيو جاز،
so stereotypically we don't have a great relationship to finance.
وبالتالي نمطيا ليس لدينا علاقة قوية بالمالية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Anyway, I just wanted to sort of point out the way that we handle it.
على كل حال، أردت فقط أن أبين نوعا ما الطريقة التي نتعامل بها مع ذلك.
And the other dynamic of it
وديناميكيته الأخرى
is that we don't micromanage in jazz.
هي أننا لا ندير الجاز بالجزئيات.
You have some people who do.
هناك بعض الناس الذين يقومون بذلك.
But what that does
لكن ما يؤدي إليه ذلك
is it actually limits the artistic possibilities.
هو في الواقع، الحد من الإمكانيات الفنية.
If I come up and I dictate to the band
إن أتيت وأمليت للفرقة
that I want to play like this and I want the music to go this way,
أنني أريد أن أعزف هذا وأنني أريد للموسيقى أن تذهب بهذا الشكل،
and I just jump right in ...
وأقفز مباشرة..
ready, just play some time.
مستعدا، فقط اعزفوا بعض الوقت.
One, two, one, two, three, four.
واحد، اثنان، واحد، اثنان، ثلاثة، أربعة.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
It's kind of chaotic because I'm bullying my ideas.
إنه نوعا ما فوضوي لأنني أسيء إلى أفكاري.
I'm telling them, "You come with me over this way."
أقول لهم، "تأتون معي لهذا الطريق."
If I really want the music to go there,
إن أردت حقا من الموسيقى أن تذهب هناك،
the best way for me to do it is to listen.
أحسن طريقة للقيام بذلك هي أن أستمع.
This is a science of listening.
هذا علم استماع.
It has far more to do with what I can perceive
يتعلق الأمر أكثر بما يمكنني تصوره
than what it is that I can do.
مما يمكنني القيام به.
So if I want the music to get to a certain level of intensity,
وبالتالي إن أردتم للموسيقى أن تصل إلى مستوى من الحدة،
the first step for me is
أول خطوة بالنسبة لي هي
to be patient, to listen to what's going on
أن تكون صبورا، أن تستمع لما يحدث
and pull from something that's going on around me.
وأسحب من شيء يحدث من حولي.
When you do that, you engage and inspire the other musicians
حين تقوم بذلك، تشرك وتلهم بقية الموسيقيين
and they give you more, and gradually it builds.
ويعطونك أكثر، وينبني ذلك تدريجيا.
Watch. One, two, a one, two, three, four.
لاحظوا. واحد، اثنان، واحد، اثنان، ثلاثة، أربعة.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Totally different experience when I'm pulling ideas.
تجربة مختلفة تماما حين أسحب الأفكار.
It's much more organic. It's much more nuanced.
إنها أكثر عضوية بكثير. وأكثر دقة بكثير.
It's not about bullying my vision or anything like that.
لا يتعلق الأمر بالإساءة إلى رؤيتي أو أي شيء من هذا القبيل.
It's about being here in the moment,
لكنه يتعلق بكونك في اللحظة،
accepting one another
نتقبل بعضنا
and allowing creativity to flow.
والسماح للإبداع بالتدفق.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)